<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--
  Copyright © 2014 <code@io7m.com> http://io7m.com

  Permission to use, copy, modify, and/or distribute this software for any
  purpose with or without fee is hereby granted, provided that the above
  copyright notice and this permission notice appear in all copies.

  THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS" AND THE AUTHOR DISCLAIMS ALL WARRANTIES
  WITH REGARD TO THIS SOFTWARE INCLUDING ALL IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF
  MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHOR BE LIABLE FOR
  ANY SPECIAL, DIRECT, INDIRECT, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OR ANY DAMAGES
  WHATSOEVER RESULTING FROM LOSS OF USE, DATA OR PROFITS, WHETHER IN AN
  ACTION OF CONTRACT, NEGLIGENCE OR OTHER TORTIOUS ACTION, ARISING OUT OF
  OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE USE OR PERFORMANCE OF THIS SOFTWARE.
  -->

<s:section 
  xml:id="r1.dai.process"
  xmlns:s="http://schemas.io7m.com/structural/2.1.0"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <s:section-title>Rendering Process</s:section-title>

  <s:paragraph>
    This section attempts to give a high-level view of the rendering
    process as it occurs in the <s:term s:type="package">${project.parent.name}</s:term> 
    package.
  </s:paragraph>

  <s:paragraph>
    A rough diagram of the rendering process for a typical program is as follows,
    with red nodes indicating actions taken by the programmer, and blue nodes
    indicating actions performed by the 
    <s:term s:type="package">${project.parent.name}</s:term> package:
  </s:paragraph>

  <s:formal-item s:kind="diagram">
    <s:formal-item-title>Rendering Flow Chart</s:formal-item-title>
    <s:image s:source="images/process_flow.png">Rendering Flow Chart</s:image>
  </s:formal-item>

  <s:paragraph>
    During the <s:term s:type="term">initialization</s:term> stage, the
    programmer is required to create a <s:term s:type="term">framebuffer</s:term>
    that will contain the results of rendering. Then, the programmer loads
    all of the <s:link s:target="r1.dai.meshes">meshes</s:link> that will be
    used during rendering <s:footnote>
      Of course, it may be that the programmer actually loads many more
      meshes during the lifetime of the application in question. This step
      is just included for the purposes of the process description.
    </s:footnote>. Then, the programmer creates instances of any
    <s:term s:type="term">renderers</s:term> and/or 
    <s:term s:type="term">postprocessors</s:term> that will be used during
    rendering.
  </s:paragraph>
  
  <s:paragraph>
    Most applications will enter into some form of 
    <s:term s:type="term">rendering loop</s:term>, where a new image is
    produced onto the screen at a rate of sixty or so per second. The
    <s:term s:type="package">${project.parent.name}</s:term> package does
    not have its own rendering loop: The programmer is simply required to
    call the renderers provided by the package whenever a new image is
    needed.
  </s:paragraph>

  <s:paragraph>
    Ordinarily, the programmer will be rendering a scene of some description.
    Most 3D simulations contain some sort of representation of a world containing
    objects and entities, with at least one observer placed within that world,
    with images produced of that world from the perspective of the observer. Almost
    certainly, the world contains some sort of 
    <s:term s:type="term">spatial data structure</s:term> that partitions
    the world into sections in order to efficiently implement collision detection
    algorithms, physics simulations, and for determining exactly which objects are
    potentially visible from the perspective of the observer. The
    <s:term s:type="package">${project.parent.name}</s:term> package remains
    completely ignorant of these details: It expects the programmer to pass it
    a list of objects and light sources to render, and does not make any attempt
    to do any spatial partitioning or visibility calculations of its own. Therefore,
    the first step taken by the programmer in most rendering loops is to work out
    exactly what needs to be rendered, and then put together a list of things that
    need to be rendered in a form that the 
    <s:term s:type="package">${project.parent.name}</s:term> package can use.
    Concretely, the programmer constructs
    <s:link s:target="r1.dai.instances">instances</s:link> (associated with
    <s:link s:target="r1.dai.materials">materials</s:link>) and
    <s:link s:target="r1.dai.lighting">lights</s:link>, placing them into
    an immutable snapshot known as a <s:link s:target="r1.dai.visible-sets">visible set</s:link>.
    Because all objects in the <s:term s:type="package">${project.parent.name}</s:term> package
    are immutable, it may be that instances, materials, and lights are re-used from the
    previous loop iteration (or submitted again with minor modifications via the use of mutable 
    builders). This is how the illusion of animated materials, lights, and instances
    are achieved in the <s:term s:type="package">${project.parent.name}</s:term> package:
    If the programmer has created a light <s:term s:type="variable">L0</s:term> in
    the previous rendering loop iteration, and submits a light <s:term s:type="variable">L1</s:term>
    in the current loop iteration that is structurally identical to 
    <s:term s:type="variable">L0</s:term> but with a slightly different intensity, then
    there will appear to be a single light in the scene with an intensity that varies over 
    time. The <s:term s:type="package">${project.parent.name}</s:term> package remains 
    completely ignorant of the passage of time and doesn't need to be concerned with 
    keeping any sort of internal state to handle animation - simplifying the 
    implementation drastically.
  </s:paragraph>
  
  <s:paragraph>
    The <s:term s:type="package">${project.parent.name}</s:term> package takes the
    immutable scene produced by the programmer and efficiently batches all of the
    instances by material, aiming to reduce the number of state changes required
    to render all of the given instances. The instances in the scene are also
    separated into <s:term s:type="term">translucent</s:term> and 
    <s:term s:type="term">opaque</s:term> groups. The programmer then passes
    this batched visible set to whichever renderer is currently being used. The renderer
    generates any shadow maps required for the lights in the visible set and then renders
    all of the opaque instances to the given framebuffer. The programmer can then
    optionally pass this framebuffer to a postprocessor if desired (to allow for
    the application of effects such as 
    <s:term s:type="term">screen space ambient occlusion</s:term>). Then, the
    programmer submits the same visible set to the renderer in order to allow
    it to render the remaining translucent instances. Again, the programmer can
    optionally pass the framebuffer to another postprocessor, or the contents of
    the framebuffer can simply be copied to the screen for display.
  </s:paragraph>

  <s:paragraph>
    Of course, the above process is simply one possible way to use the
    <s:term s:type="package">${project.parent.name}</s:term> package. Real
    applications might use the renderers to produce images that will then
    be re-used in further visible sets. For example, if a visible set uses materials that
    use <s:link s:target="r1.dai.environment-mapping">environment mapping</s:link>,
    the programmer might pass six drastically simplified versions of a scene
    to the renderer in order to produce the six faces of a 
    <s:term s:type="term">cube map</s:term>.
    This cube map may then be used in materials that are used with instances
    to render a visible set that will actually be displayed to the screen.
  </s:paragraph>

</s:section>