<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--
  Copyright © 2014 <code@io7m.com> http://io7m.com

  Permission to use, copy, modify, and/or distribute this software for any
  purpose with or without fee is hereby granted, provided that the above
  copyright notice and this permission notice appear in all copies.

  THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS" AND THE AUTHOR DISCLAIMS ALL WARRANTIES
  WITH REGARD TO THIS SOFTWARE INCLUDING ALL IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF
  MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHOR BE LIABLE FOR
  ANY SPECIAL, DIRECT, INDIRECT, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OR ANY DAMAGES
  WHATSOEVER RESULTING FROM LOSS OF USE, DATA OR PROFITS, WHETHER IN AN
  ACTION OF CONTRACT, NEGLIGENCE OR OTHER TORTIOUS ACTION, ARISING OUT OF
  OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE USE OR PERFORMANCE OF THIS SOFTWARE.
  -->

<s:section 
  xml:id="r1.dai.materials"
  xmlns:s="http://schemas.io7m.com/structural/2.1.0"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <s:section-title>Materials</s:section-title>
  <s:section-contents/>

  <s:subsection xml:id="r1.dai.materials.overview">
    <s:subsection-title>Overview</s:subsection-title>
    <s:paragraph>
      This section attempts to provide information on the
      <s:term s:type="term">material</s:term> system used in the
      <s:term s:type="package">io7m-r1</s:term> package
      as well as the rationale for its existence.
    </s:paragraph>
    <s:paragraph>
      In contrast to most other rendering systems, the
      <s:term s:type="package">io7m-r1</s:term> package
      uses a typed <s:term s:type="term">material</s:term> system configured
      directly from code, rather than having programmers and artists write 
      <s:term s:type="term">shaders</s:term> in a shading language directly. It was a
      conscious design decision to reduce <s:term s:type="term">flexibility</s:term>
      in order to increase <s:term s:type="term">ease of use</s:term> and
      <s:term s:type="term">correctness</s:term>. The material system
      has the following disadvantages:
    </s:paragraph>
    <s:formal-item s:kind="lists">
      <s:formal-item-title>Material system disadvantages</s:formal-item-title>
      <s:list-unordered>
        <s:list-item>
          The material system was designed to accomodate the majority
          of rendering techniques seen in computer games circa 2014 (such as
          normal mapping, environment mapped reflections, etc). If the
          <s:term s:type="package">io7m-r1</s:term> package
          doesn't provide direct support for a technique, then the programmer
          is required to modify the <s:term s:type="package">io7m-r1</s:term> 
          package to use it.
        </s:list-item>
      </s:list-unordered>
    </s:formal-item>
    <s:paragraph>
      However, the design also allows for the following advantages:
    </s:paragraph>
    <s:formal-item s:kind="lists">
      <s:formal-item-title>Material system advantages</s:formal-item-title>
      <s:list-unordered>
        <s:list-item>
          The material system was designed to accomodate the majority
          of rendering techniques seen in computer games circa 2014 (such as
          normal mapping, environment mapped reflections, etc). Rather than
          having to tediously re-implement error-prone techniques such as 
          normal mapping over and over, the programmer simply enables
          normal mapping for a material.
        </s:list-item>
        <s:list-item>
          The material system provides enough <s:term s:type="term">metadata</s:term>
          about a given surface for all renderers in the
          <s:term s:type="package">io7m-r1</s:term> package to
          give consistently correct results regardless of the lighting in a scene. 
          For example, other rendering
          systems that utilize <s:term s:type="term">shadow mapping</s:term>
          often give incorrect results when a user-written shader conditionally
          <s:term s:type="term">discards</s:term> pixels. Shadow mapping is implemented
          by rendering a depth-only image of an object from a different perspective,
          and so the same pixels have to be discarded when rendering the depth-only 
          image as when rendering the actual color image. In systems where the
          user is required to write shaders, the system has no way of knowing that
          some pixels need to be discarded and often has to fall back to running
          the full material shader with writes to the color buffer masked.
          The material system
          in the <s:term s:type="package">io7m-r1</s:term> package
          indicates <s:term s:type="term">statically</s:term> when this can occur,
          and so the system simply uses a very efficient depth-only shader to
          render accurate shadow maps.
        </s:list-item>
        <s:list-item>
          In other rendering systems (particularly those that use 
          <s:term s:type="term">forward rendering</s:term>), the programmer is
          required to write one shader per combination of <s:term s:type="term">material</s:term>
          and <s:term s:type="term">light</s:term>. That is, the programmer
          is expected to re-implement each of the different lighting techniques
          for every single material so that each can be used in any possible lighting environment. 
          Many systems use a shader generation system
          to work around these sorts of problems, requiring the development of
          (and the programmer to learn) even more complex tools and development environments.
          This issue is simply not present with a static material system.
        </s:list-item>
        <s:list-item>
          Because the set of possible material and light types in the
          <s:term s:type="package">io7m-r1</s:term> package is
          fixed, the system knows exactly how to correctly send data to all
          of the possible <s:term s:type="term">shaders</s:term>. The programmer
          is not required to laboriously configure all of the connections between
          shader parameters and the data that must be supplied to shaders. All of
          the usual classes of bugs involving forgetting to set parameters, sending
          parameters of the wrong type, etc, are simply not possible.
        </s:list-item>
        <s:list-item>
          The material system allows for extremely rapid development and
          previewing of materials. Because the components of the material
          systems are exposed as simple pseudo-algebraic Java types, it is
          extremely easy to put together a graphical user interface for
          configuring materials. Rendering systems that require programmers
          to write shaders typically end up implementing their own complete
          integrated development environments!
        </s:list-item>
        <s:list-item>
          Because the GLSL language is fundamentally poorly designed and entirely
          anti-modular, any rendering system requiring the programmer to write
          shaders must implement its own custom shading language to give good
          type errors and to work identically across all of the different possible
          versions of OpenGL
          <s:footnote>
            The <s:term s:type="package">io7m-r1</s:term> package
            actually uses the <s:link-external s:target="http://mvn.io7m.com/io7m-jparasol">Parasol</s:link-external>
            language internally to avoid the mentioned issues, but does not expose
            this to programmers using the package.
          </s:footnote>. It is simply not possible, in the <s:term s:type="package">io7m-r1</s:term> package,
          for the programmer to create a material that will work on some of the
          supported OpenGL versions and not others.
        </s:list-item>
        <s:list-item>
          The material system has predictable performance characteristics. In
          systems that require programmers to write their own shaders, it is
          standard practice for programmers to repeatedly re-visit and do
          tedious optimization work to get their materials to run faster. The
          <s:term s:type="package">io7m-r1</s:term> package
          tries to expose a very minimalist material system and delegates the
          work of, for example, procedural texture generation to external systems
          <s:footnote>
            This has the advantage that, if a texture is procedurally generated
            by an external system, the texture can be cached and re-used by many
            different surfaces. This is obviously not possible in systems that
            do all of that work during the actual rendering of an object.
          </s:footnote>.
        </s:list-item>
      </s:list-unordered>
    </s:formal-item>
    <s:paragraph>
      The <s:term s:type="package">io7m-r1</s:term> package is
      generally developed under the assumption that if a programmer is competent
      enough to write all of their own shading and lighting algorithms, then they
      might as well have written their own rendering system in the first place
      <s:footnote>
        There is a tension in rendering systems between providing something that
        is restrictive but easy to use, and providing something that is so 
        generalized that it is capable of anything but barely any easier to use
        than using the OpenGL API directly.
      </s:footnote>!
    </s:paragraph>
  </s:subsection>

  <s:subsection xml:id="r1.dai.materials.types">
    <s:subsection-title>Types</s:subsection-title>
    <s:paragraph>
      All materials implement
      <s:link-external s:target="apidocs/com/io7m/r1/kernel/types/KMaterialType.html">KMaterialType</s:link-external>.
    </s:paragraph>
    <s:paragraph xml:id="r1.dai.materials.types.matrix">
      All materials have a 3x3 texture matrix which is concatenated with
      a per-instance 3x3 texture matrix during rendering. The texture
      matrix affects all textures (such as the <s:term s:type="term">albedo map</s:term>,
      <s:term s:type="term">normal map</s:term>, <s:term s:type="term">specular map</s:term>, etc)
      in the material simultaneously. This allows for the orientation, scale
      and position of a texture to be set on a per-material basis, and then
      adjusted on a per-instance basis later.
    </s:paragraph>
    <s:paragraph>
      All materials have a unique <s:term s:type="term">material code</s:term>
      (a simple string) that allows the rendering system to select a 
      <s:term s:type="term">shader</s:term> in 
      <s:term s:type="expression">O(1)</s:term> time to render the material.
    </s:paragraph>
    <s:paragraph>
      All materials take the form <s:term s:type="term">pseudo-algebraic</s:term>
      data types, with each <s:term s:type="term">case</s:term> (or 
      <s:term s:type="term">constructor</s:term> in typed functional languages - not used here
      because the term already exists in Java and means something else) being
      represented by a single type. For example, the type of
      <s:term s:type="term">albedo</s:term> material properties is represented
      by the <s:link-external s:target="apidocs/com/io7m/r1/kernel/types/KMaterialAlbedoType.html">KMaterialAlbedoType</s:link-external>
      type, with specific cases represented by the
      <s:link-external s:target="apidocs/com/io7m/r1/kernel/types/KMaterialAlbedoTextured.html">KMaterialAlbedoTextured</s:link-external>
      and
      <s:link-external s:target="apidocs/com/io7m/r1/kernel/types/KMaterialAlbedoUntextured.html">KMaterialAlbedoUntextured</s:link-external>
      types. When given a value of type
      <s:term s:type="constant">KMaterialAlbedoType</s:term>, it is necessary to
      <s:term s:type="term">pattern-match</s:term> on the value to find out which
      of the specific types the value actually is. This is achieved in Java by the
      use of <s:term s:type="term">generic visitors</s:term>. As an example:
    </s:paragraph>
    <s:formal-item s:kind="examples">
      <s:formal-item-title>Pattern matching</s:formal-item-title>
      <s:verbatim><xi:include href="examples/Match0.java" parse="text"/></s:verbatim>
    </s:formal-item>
    <s:paragraph>
      Essentially, the method <s:term s:type="constant">albedoAccept</s:term> is
      passed a value <s:term s:type="expression">v</s:term> of type
      <s:link-external s:target="apidocs/com/io7m/r1/kernel/types/KMaterialAlbedoVisitorType.html">KMaterialAlbedoVisitorType</s:link-external>.
      The <s:term s:type="constant">textured</s:term> method of 
      <s:term s:type="expression">v</s:term> is called if 
      <s:term s:type="expression">m</s:term> is of type
      <s:term s:type="constant">KMaterialAlbedoTextured</s:term>, and
      the <s:term s:type="constant">untextured</s:term> method of 
      <s:term s:type="expression">v</s:term> is called if 
      <s:term s:type="expression">m</s:term> is of type
      <s:term s:type="constant">KMaterialAlbedoUntextured</s:term>. The
      methods of <s:term s:type="expression">v</s:term> can return values
      of type <s:term s:type="expression">A</s:term> (in this case, because
      the visitor simply prints a message and doesn't return anything, the
      visitor returns a value of type <s:term s:type="expression">Unit</s:term>),
      and can raise exceptions of type 
      <s:term s:type="expression">E</s:term> (in this case, the visitor does
      not raise any exceptions and so throws an unchecked
      <s:term s:type="expression">UnreachableCodeException</s:term>).
    </s:paragraph>
    <s:paragraph>
      This method of representing types with a small number of fixed cases
      is used throughout the <s:term s:type="package">io7m-r1</s:term> 
      package <s:footnote>
        Please see <s:link-external s:target="http://io7m.com/documents/types/ccat/">A Crash Course in Algebraic Types</s:link-external>,
        and more or less any software written in a typed functional languages for
        a description of the immense correctness and maintenance benefits that 
        algebraic data types provide.
      </s:footnote>.
    </s:paragraph>
    <s:paragraph>
      Materials are divided into <s:term s:type="term">opaque</s:term> and
      <s:term s:type="term">translucent</s:term> types, represented by the
      <s:link-external s:target="apidocs/com/io7m/r1/kernel/types/KMaterialOpaqueType.html">KMaterialOpaqueType</s:link-external>
      and
      <s:link-external s:target="apidocs/com/io7m/r1/kernel/types/KMaterialTranslucentType.html">KMaterialTranslucentType</s:link-external>
      types. Specific cases of the <s:term s:type="term">translucent</s:term> types
      allow for effects such as <s:term s:type="term">specular-only</s:term> 
      rendering (<s:link-external s:target="apidocs/com/io7m/r1/kernel/types/KMaterialTranslucentSpecularOnly.html">KMaterialTranslucentSpecularOnly</s:link-external>)
      and <s:link s:target="r1.dai.generic-refraction">generic refraction</s:link>
      (<s:link-external s:target="apidocs/com/io7m/r1/kernel/types/KMaterialTranslucentRefractive.html">KMaterialTranslucentRefractive</s:link-external>).
    </s:paragraph>
  </s:subsection>

  <s:subsection xml:id="r1.dai.materials.shaders">
    <s:subsection-title>Shaders</s:subsection-title>
    <s:paragraph>
      In order to render an object on modern graphics hardware,
      it's necessary to use one or more <s:term s:type="term">shaders</s:term>
      (<s:term s:type="term">shading programs</s:term>) to actually
      render surface details and/or apply lighting.
    </s:paragraph>
    <s:paragraph>
      When performing <s:link s:target="r1.dai.forward-translucents">forward rendering</s:link>,
      one shader is used per combination of surface material type and
      <s:link s:target="r1.dai.lighting">light type</s:link>. When performing
      <s:link s:target="r1.dai.deferred">deferred rendering</s:link>, one
      shader is used to render the surface properties into a buffer, and another
      shader is used to calculate lighting using the data in the buffer.
    </s:paragraph>
    <s:paragraph>
      It's therefore necessary to be able to, given an arbitrary material and light,
      efficiently choose shaders with which to perform rendering. Because
      all possible material and light combinations in the 
      <s:term s:type="package">io7m-r1</s:term> package are
      known ahead of time, the <s:term s:type="package">io7m-r1</s:term> 
      package simply picks one from the complete set of possible shaders that were generated
      when the package was built. When an object with a given material <s:term s:type="variable">m</s:term>
      is placed into a scene, the <s:term s:type="package">io7m-r1</s:term> package
      reads the <s:term s:type="term">material code</s:term> (a simple unique identifier string)
      for the material and uses that code to select a shader. The shader is
      then compiled, loaded, and cached. The next time a material 
      (or material and light combination) appears with the same code, the 
      cached shader is re-used.
    </s:paragraph>
    <s:paragraph>
      The advantage of this approach, somewhat ironically, is a reduction
      in the number of shaders that have to be loaded at any given time. In
      other rendering systems that equate materials with shaders, a scene
      containing a thousand different material types requires a thousand
      different shaders to be loaded (even though many of those shaders may
      be functionally identical). The same scene using the material system
      in the <s:term s:type="package">io7m-r1</s:term> package
      may only require dozens of shaders, because a shader essentially 
      represents a combination of material properties 
      (such as "normal mapped, environment mapped, textured albedo"), 
      as opposed to representing an entire material. This also reduces the
      number of rendering state changes that have to be performed during
      rendering: If two materials differ structurally only in the actual 
      textures that they use, then the same shader will be used for both
      and therefore the rendering system does not need to switch shaders
      during rendering to render objects using either material.
    </s:paragraph>
  </s:subsection>

</s:section>
